Guide to the Alumni Scrapbook and Alumni Association Minutes RG.40.1.1
New York University Archives
Alumni Scrapbook and Alumni Association Minutes
1839-1934
New York University Archives
New York University. Alumni Association
RG.40.1.1
2.50 Linear Feet in six boxes
This collection consists primarily of the earliest minutes, correspondence and records of the Alumni Association of New York University (then, the University of the City of New York). This collection is divided into two series. Series I consists of the The Alumni Association Scrapbook and dates from 1846 to 1856. This series was compiled by William R. Martin, secretary of the Association, in 1886. Series II consists of the Alumni Association Minutes and dates from 1834 to 1934. This series is arranged chronologically.
Access Restrictions
Open for use without restrictions. Some materials in Series II of the collection are fragile and may require supervision when handling.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series. Series I consists of the Alumni Scrapbook, organized in one box with each individual page placed into its own folder. Series II consists of the Alumni Association Meeting Minutes and has been divided into five separate boxes and is ordered chronologically.
History of the University of the City of New York Association of Alumni
The New York University (then the University of the City of New York) Association of Alumni Scrapbook dates from 1846 to 1856 and was compiled by William R. Martin, Secretary of the Association, in 1886. The scrapbook consists of the earliest records of the Association, including the earliest copy of the constitution, draft resolutions, election ballots, as well as correspondence between various officers. New York University notables represented in the Scrapbook include: S.F.B. Morse, J.W. Draper, John Taylor Johnston, Theodore Frelinghuysen, Isaac Ferris, and Cornelius Mathews.
Cornelius Mathews was the first president of the Alumni Association. He graduated from New York University in 1834 and is an American writer best known for his role in the formation of the literary group Young America in the late 1830s, as well as for his support of a distinctly American style of literary expression.
Theodore Frelinghuysen served as a United States Senator from 1829 to 1835, representing New Jersey, and was nominated as the United States Secretary of State in 1881. He served as the Chancellor of New York University from 1839 to 1850. He is represented in the Scrapbook through both his letters to the Association as well as through his participation in the Smith Lectures.
Isaac Ferris was a clergyman in the Reformed Dutch Church of America as well as a University administrator. He was the Chancellor of New York University from 1853 until 1870. He is represented in the Scrapbook through both his letters to the Association as well as through his participation in commencement-related activities.
John William Draper was a scientist, historian and photographer. He served as both a professor and president of the New York University School of Medicine. He is represented in the Scrapbook through his letters to the Association as well as through his address to alumni.
Samuel Morse was an accomplished artist and founder of the National Academy of Design. He is also credited as the co-inventor of Morse code, as well as co-contributor to the invention of the single-wire telegraph. At New York University, Morse lectured widely on art and was appointed, in 1832, as Chair of Sculpture and Painting at the University. He is represented in the Scrapbook through his correspondence with various faculty members and alumni.
The Alumni Association Scrapbook also largely consists of material related to the Smith Lectures. Joseph E. Smith was a janitor at New York University for 35 years. Upon his retirement, the Alumni Association, in appreciation of his service, purchased a farm for Smith, to be paid for by subscription. Unfortunately, not enough money was raised through subscription, so the Executive Committee resolved to institute a series of public lectures, which were to be given gratis by distinguished University alumni. The proceeds from tbe ticket sales of these lectures were used to clear the remaining debt for the farm.
The Alumni Association Minutes date from the earliest meetings of the Association and its Executive Committee. They are divided into five boxes, which have been arranged chronologically.
Related Materials at the New York University Archives
Researchers interested in this collection may also be interested in MC 76, the Isaac Ferris Papers; MC 11, the Draper Family Collection (1836-1982), as well MC 10, the Samuel F.B. Morse Papers (1838-1984).
Scope and Contents
This collection of records of the Alumni Association of New York University consists of the early records of the Association and dates from 1839 to 1934. This collection is organized into two separate series.
Series I consists of the Alumni Scrapbook and dates from 1846 to 1886. The Alumni Scrapbook was compiled by William R. Martin, secretary of the Association, in 1886. It consists primarily of the early records of the Association, including its constitution, draft resolutions and correspondence between various officers. Historical figures represented in the scrapbook include: S.F.B. Morse, J.W. Draper, John Taylor Johnston, Theodore Frelinghuysen, Isaac Ferris, and various other notables. The Alumni Scrapbook also consists of the Smith Lectures, a series of public lectures arranged by the Association and given by distinguished Alumni in order to raise proceeds to purchase a farm for Joseph E. Smith, janitor at NYU for 35 years, in appreciation of his service to the University.
Due to both the great historical importance of the papers as well their deteriorating condition, each individual page has been removed and placed in its own acid-free folder. However, the order of the materials has not been disturbed, and each folder now bears the number of the page of the scrapbook whose contents it contains.
Series II of this collection consists of the Alumni Association Minutes and dates from 1846-1934. This series is organized into five seperate boxes, each arranged in chronological order and containing one bound copy of Association meeting minutes. Each bound copy is fragile and must be handled with care.
Commencement ceremonies; Minutes (administrative records); Newspapers.; NYU Press; Ferris, Isaac, 1798-1873; Frelinghuysen, Theodore, 1787-1862; Draper, John William, 1811-1882; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; New York University -- Alumni and alumnae -- Periodicals; New York University -- History -- Lectures
- Series I: Alumni Scrapbook, 1839-1886
  - Portrait of Dodge, R., undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - First alumni oration by Cornelius Mathews, 15 July 1839 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Original minutes by Marcus L. Taft, July 1, 1846 and June 29, 1847, Robert Dodge; letters, August 17-19, 1847, July 1846-August 1847 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original minutes, 28 June 1848 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Draft minutes, 1 July 1846 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters: Cornelius Mathews 3 July 1846 and W.B. Maclay July 9 1846 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters: Robert Dodge, Thos Tomlinson, 22 July 1846 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters: M.L. Taft, 19 Sept. 1846, Cyrus Mason, 25 Sept. 1846, September 1846 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Constitution drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Earliest copy of Constitution, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letter: Robert Dodge, 17 March 1847 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual Meeting, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, Executive Committee meeting, 29 June 1848 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters: M.L. Taft, 19 April 1849, W.B. Maclay, 27 April, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters: A. Cleveland Coxe, 28 April 1849, John Taylor Johnson, 1 May 1849; Report of Executive Committee, 14 May 1849, April 1849-May 1849 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters: John Taylor Johnston and A.C. Coxe, June 1849, George F. Davenport, 28 June 1849 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Draft of circular by Moore, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Minutes, 27 June 1849 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Taft obit, 23 May 1849 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letter: Knapp, 18 August 1851 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters of John Taylor Johnston, 8 May 1851 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters: A.C. Coxe, 10 June 1850, Doremus, 6 June 1850 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters: Aikman, 27 June 1850; Minutes, 26 June 1850 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Draft resolution, 26 June 1850 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Election Ballot, 26 June 1850 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters: Townsend, 22 July 1852; Butler, 30 Sept. 1851; Address, Crosby, 1851, Sept 1851-July 1852 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters: Huntington, 21 February 1852; Russel, 22 May 1852; Huntington, 20 August 1886, February 1852-August 1886 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letter: Johnston, 30 June 1852 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Treasurer's a/c, 30 June 1852 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Constitution; Report of Executive Committee, 30 June 1852 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Draft resolutions, 20 June 1852 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - First Alumni dinner, 30 June 1852 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Speeches: Senator McMurray, Elias Loomis, 30 June 1852 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Alumni Dinner Speech, Crosby, 30 June 1852 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Alumni Dinner Speech, A. Oakley Hall and Cornelius Mathews, 30 June 1852 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Alumni Dinner, treasurer's a/c, 30 June 1852 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Letters: Moore, Huntington, Crosby, July 1852-August 1852 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Letters: Caleb S. Henry, June 1852-October 1852 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Letters: Coxe andDraper, Sept. 1852-Nov. 1852 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Address, C.S. Henry, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Letters: Ferris, Johnson, Draper, March 1853-June 1853 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Letters: Draper, Leeds, Morse, June 1853 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Letters: Frelinghuysen, 21 June 1853 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 21st Anniversary, programme and invitation, 29 June 1853 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Draper Address, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Executive Committee Election Ballot, 29 June 1853 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Annual Meeting Draft Resolutions, 29 June 1853 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Annual Meeting Subscriptions, 29 June 1853 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Alumni Dinner, 29 June 1853 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Dr. Draper's Address, newspaper clippings, 29 June 1853 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Letters: Draper, Martin, Hist. Soc. Penn, Sept. 1853-March 1854 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Letters: President Wayland, Sept. 1853 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Chancellor Ferris Circular, October 1853 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Letter, Van Buren; Speech, Mathews, 29 June 1853 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Election ballot; draft resolutions, 27 June 1854 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Letter, Chancellor Ferris, 28 June 1854 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Subscription Paper, 27 June 1854 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Commencement Clippings, 28 June 1854 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Minutes, 27 June 1855 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Letter, J.M. Mathews, 23 May 1855 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Smith Lectures, January 1855 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Smith Lectures, Executive Committee, 27 Jan 1855 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Smith Lectures, Replies, January 1855-March 1855 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Smith Lectures; Letters: Frelinghuysen, Abbott, January 1855-March 1855 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Smith Lectures, Replies, February 1855 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Smith Lectures, Replies, February 1855 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Smith Lectures, Letters: Crosby, Abbott, 13 Feb 1855 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Smith Lectures, Letters: Hall, Crosby, Fell, February 1855-March 1855 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Smith lectures, newspaper clippings, March 1855 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Smith lectures, newspaper clippings, April 1855 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Smith lectures, newspaper clippings, April 1855 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Smith Lectures, newspaper clippings, April 1855 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Smith Lectures, report account, April 1855 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Annual meeting, executive committee report, 2 July 1856 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Annual Meeting, report on law school, 3 July 1856 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Commencement, newspaper clippings, 4 July 1856 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Herald report of Commencement, 3 July 1856 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Thomas B. Stirling, address and biographical note, 2 July 1856 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Association of the Alumni of CUNY, constitution, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Mathews biographical sketch, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Benjamin N. Martin address, 27 June 1854 (Box 1, Folder 81)
- Series II: Alumni Association Minutes, 1846-1934
  - Minutes of the Alumni Association Standing Committee, 1846-1856 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Association Minutes, 1834-1875 (Box 2)
  - Alumni Association Minutes, 1876-1886 (Box 3)
  - Alumni Association Minutes, 1896-1921 (Box 4)
  - Alumni Association Minutes, 1926-1934 (Box 5)